<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition published by the Generall States of the Netherlandish Vnited Prouinces, vnto the states, and citties their aduersaries touching his now intended proceedings, against the Spaniards and their adherents : whereunto is annexed a caueat, or proclamation, to the Vnited Netherlandish Prouinces / translated out of the Dutch printed coppy.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18454.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23190090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23190090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition published by the Generall States of the Netherlandish Vnited Prouinces, vnto the states, and citties their aduersaries touching his now intended proceedings, against the Spaniards and their adherents : whereunto is annexed a caueat, or proclamation, to the Vnited Netherlandish Prouinces / translated out of the Dutch printed coppy.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Dight, and are to be solde by Thomas Pauier, at his shop at the signe of the cat and parrets, neere the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26362:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26362:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <p>An Admonition pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed <hi>by the Generall States of the</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish vnited Prouinces: vnto the States, and Citties their aduerſaries: touching his now intended proceedings, againſt the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and their adherents.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed a caueat, or Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the Vnited Netherlandiſh Prouinces.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Dutch Printed Coppy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Walter Dight, and are to be ſolde by Thomas Pauier, at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Cat and Parrets neere the Royall-Exchange. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26362:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26362:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>
               <hi>An admonition publiſhed by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> States of the Netherlandish-Vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces: vnto the States and Citties, their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, touching his now intended proceedings, againſt the Spaniards &amp; their adherents.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the high and-well borne, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend, Noble, right Worſhip. moſt learned, Wiſe, Prouident, moſt diſcreete Lordes, good friends &amp; neighbors: The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Princes, Earles, Lords, Gentlemen and Citties of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Flaunders, Artois, Haynolt, Valenchien, Lylle, Donay, Orchies, Namen, Tornezie, Tournay and Mecheld, repreſenting the States of the Netherlands, vnder the gouernment of the Spaniards or the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke: &amp; to euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in generall &amp; perticular.</salute>
               <salute>MOſt high and well-borne, Reuerend, Noble, right worſhipfull, worthy, learned, wiſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, and moſt diſcreete Lords, good friendes and louing neighbours:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We doubt not but your Excellen. Lordſh, worſh. &amp; beloued are: yet minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the manifolde amiable exhortations done vnto you by vs at ſeuerall times, tending to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke your Excellencies, Lordſhips, worſhips &amp;c. onely once with a ripe and ſettled ſence, to conſider the wicked pretences of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> &amp; their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents: enemies to the welfare, rights, preui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb facs="tcp:26362:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->goods, and perſons of the Netherlands: namely, vtterly to deſtroy &amp; ruinate (generallie) all the inhabitants of the Netherlandes, of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, quallitie, or condition ſo euer: which indeede hath been their originall, &amp; deep noted miſchieuous and ſhamefull pretence.</p>
            <p>It is not alſo vnknowne to vs (although the ſaid pretence be nothing leſſe beleeued, &amp; helde for moſt vnreplicable amongſt you then with vs) that yet notwithſtanding ſome of your Excellencies, Worſhips &amp;c. Partly through the naturall inſtinct of their Noble kindenes, and partly by perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are reduced to a ſelfe feeling knowledge &amp;c. &amp; that through the Archdukes meanes, and their highneſſes preſences, theſe matters might be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and brought to a better point. But conſidering that we haue a perfect knowledge of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Spaniſh pretence which ceaſeth not, but with their adherents (by all meanes) ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to procure the ruine &amp; ouerthrow of theſe Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, thereby for euer to reduce them to the thral-dome of the Spaniſh yoake, and according to their owne appetites &amp; pleaſures to rule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not onely ouer the good inhabiatantes of the ſame, but alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, bodies, rights &amp; goods, which the Archduke himſelfe ſhall not be able to preuent nor remedie. Wee haue not been able to conforme our ſelues to any ſuch liking but to the ende your Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies Lordſhips, worſhips &amp;c. nor our ſelues, be not throwne downe headlong into an eminent, Infallible, continuall, &amp; vnrecouerable ouerthrowe and ſeruitude, we hauing compaſſionatly found it better (with a ſtedfaſt courage) to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; perſiſt inour laudable reſolution, originally, ſprung from
<pb facs="tcp:26362:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->the chiefeſt &amp; notableſt Perſons &amp; members of the generall Netherlandiſh Prouinces of all eſtates &amp; conditions. Truſting aſſuredly vpon the mercifull helpe of the Almightie God: vpon the fauours, aides, &amp; aſſiſtaunces of the Kings, Princes, and common wealthes, with which we are in league, &amp; friendſhip, together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the iuſtnes of our cauſe: &amp; with all patience to expect (eſpecially by meanes of your Excellencies, Lorſhips, Worſhips &amp;c. good furtherance, direction, &amp; inward wiſe gouerment in your ſtates) a godlie &amp; moſt wiſhed iſſue thereof. And to that ende moſt willinglie to beare all the burthens, perrils, charges, &amp; paynes: which in ſo holly, laudable, honourable, ſeruiceable, &amp; needfull a reſolution ſhal be requiſite: without that at any time we haue, or euer ſhallbe mooued to any kinde of alteration, by meanes of that vnworthy tranſportation, done of theſe Netherlands, by the late king of <hi>Spaine</hi> vnto their Highneſſes: we hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in regard of the ſame (after the ſaid tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) by our letters &amp; <hi>verball</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications, held with your Exe Lo. Mo. &amp;c. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners: earneſtly admoniſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good care might be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of war on your ſides, aſwel within &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the land: &amp; we truſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if the ſame were cenſured with an vnpaſſionate &amp; vnpartial mind, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cleare eyes wel looked into, none were able vprighly to iudge, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid deceiptful tranſportation was vnce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable tending to the aſſured and eminent ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw &amp; ſuppreſſion of the general Netherlands, &amp; of all eſtates and perſons therein. Your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. manifeſtly ſee, heare, vnderſtand &amp; feele, what paſſeth among you, &amp; you
<pb facs="tcp:26362:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->are able eaſily to coniecture what elſe is apparant to follow: in ſo much that we eſteeme it needles to write any tedious circumſtance therof. Onely, as yet we will moſt friendly wiſh, exhort &amp; pray your Excellen. Lord. Morſh. &amp;c. earneſtly to conſider the worthy &amp; laudable reputation, which by your Exc. Lor. Mor &amp;c. and our fore-fathers, hath bin pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed ſo many hundred yeeres a goe: &amp; vntill this preſent is left vs a leuelled lyne, for vs to follow therby, &amp; to be come true Champions &amp; defendors of the free Netherlandiſh rights &amp; priuiledges in generall: and perticularly of the countries, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, citties, &amp; the inhabitants thereof. And to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine if the contents of the ſaid anullated and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy tranſportation, and the dealings which ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence haue followed (&amp; yet dayly are continuing) do agree together, with the duties wherwith your Excel. Lord. Wor. &amp;c. their worthy houſen, eſtates, poſterities (but eſpecially our beloued naturall country) is bound vnto: if yee, (which we by no meanes can perſwade our ſelues vnto) wee muſt beſeech God Almighty of his mercy to illuminate &amp; endue your Excel. Lor. Wor. &amp;c. with a more ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der iudgement and vnderſtanding: But if in caſe your Exc. Lo. Wo doiudge the ſaid pretended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy tranſportatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (although it hath bin accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through neceſſity, d to ſhun a further or greater miſchiefe) to be diſhonorable, deceiptful, &amp; a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpot &amp; blemiſh vnto al worthy Netherlanders: Conſidered moreouer, that the proceedinges of the Spaniards &amp; their adherents follow theron, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this preſent, do continue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bad to worſe, aſwel in matters of State as in war, are (as we aſſure
<pb facs="tcp:26362:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->our ſelues, that moſt of your Excellences, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. well know) are altogether ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous &amp; intollerable: And conſequently your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. are not bound nor beholden vnto them, as thoſe which warre and ſtriue againſt the generall good, and the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh</hi> Lawes, Rights, and Priuiledges. If like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe your Excellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. conſider how all the extremitie of Forces, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictors of trade and commerce, con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piracies and plots, to intrap her princel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maieſtie of <hi>England,</hi> and th'united Prou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces, dayly appeare and are diſcouered: and not only their pretences are vaine and forceleſſe, but allo haue a quite contrarie ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. That the treacherous enterpriſes vpon Citties and Forts of the <hi>French</hi> Kings, giue great occaſion, that ſome day or other, a ſodaine &amp; tirrible reuenge may be vndertaken. That the Bookes, and famous Libels and odious Ballades, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſeeke to make the <hi>French</hi> King and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges, hatefull in the Commons hartes, and to make the Rights of Succeſſion of the Crownes of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>England</hi> doubtfull, are nothing e<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e but idle prepoſitions, onely tending to the irita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prouoking of their Maieſties: And that in vaine it is attempted, to rayſe tumultes and diſſentions among the Communaltie of th'united Prouinces, ſince that the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (prayſe vnto Go<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) their Conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſidered, are in eſtate a hundred times better, and more aſſured, then the Communaltie on the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> or their Highneſſes ſide: and that they not hauing any reaſon of miſtruſt in their lawfull Magiſtrates, nor of their actions, do beare
<pb facs="tcp:26362:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->themſelues moſt quiet and obedient. But that to the contrarie, the Commons of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> or Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukes ſide beeing that all matters do dayly ware worſe and worſe,) That the authoritie of the States, Prelats, Princes, Lordes, Nobles, and Citties, of the Counties both generally and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly, more then euer toſore, is troden vnder foote and reduced to no regard nor reſpect. Yea, that a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l matters haue their foundation and ground vpon Straungers, with a deiection of all worthie Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and home-borne Nobilitie, not only in the gouernement of the pricipall Citties and Fortes, but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ufficiently in generall in euery thing: except that ſometime heere and there <hi>Proforma,</hi> in ſome matters they ſeeme to doe ſome thing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the which alſo (they once beeing Maiſters) would ſoone leaue aſide.</p>
            <p>That the Countries and Inhabitants are rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, diſrobed, and disfurniſhed, not onely of a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l trafficke, negotiation, nauigation, welfare, and dealings; but alſo the very three fourth partes of the good Inhabitantes, are vtterly deſtitute of all meanes of maintenaunce. The principall Citties conu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rted to Doue-cots, the Villages and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie groundes euen brought to the extreameſt poynt of pouertie, eaten vp and ranſackt by the men of Warre: and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et the Soul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iers themſelues to ill payde, that the <unclear>mutenie</unclear> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one partie cannot be appea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, but there are two l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, or worſe, to be expected. And that in brie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, it is moſt euident, that all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill fall into a moſt apparant dangerous deſperation.</p>
            <p>This then all conſidered, we pray your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,
<pb facs="tcp:26362:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. that in effect, the nee<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efull remedies heereto may be taken in hand and miniſtred. And namely, that it may pleaſe you to effect thus much, as that their Highneſſe will vouchſafe to depart out of the <hi>Netherlandes,</hi> to purchaſe a more quieter and ſecurer partage or portion: At which time, it wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be little difficult for your Excellencies, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. and vs together, to make the <hi>Spaniards</hi> &amp; other Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to follow them: and for the beſt part of their adherentes, to make and conuert vnto good and worthy <hi>Netherlanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If now by any one this were helde for an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitie, &amp; that your Excel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>encies, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. could not ſecurely take, nor vſe this courte; that it may pleaſe them then to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to beleeue: that if in caſe your Excellen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, Lor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps, Worſhips, &amp;c. will furniſh vs with ſo much Money and meanes for ſixe Monethes, as importes the halfe of the oulde or<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inarie Taxe of <hi>Brabant,Flaunders, Artois, Haynolt, Valencinen, Lylle, Douay, Orchies, Namen, Tournez<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> and <hi>Mechelen,</hi> to the ſame: which through Gods gracious permiſſion, we inten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eere to performe in maner of Warre: And in reſpect of their Highneſſes, keepe themſelues quiet, or tall to vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (which we put to your Excellencies, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c choyce and good lyking, that the matter by Go<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s helpe) ſhall be brought to that paſſe, that your Excellencies, Lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dſhips, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, &amp;c. themſelues, ſhal iu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge therein to be moſt apparant lignes of good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>And touching th'aſſurance, whereon diuers
<pb facs="tcp:26362:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->kinde harted and well enclyned perſons trouble themſelues, are kept backe and ſtand reſelute, your Excellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. ſhall them ſelues ſet or hold ſuch orders, as well of the Gouernement as of Religon, as themſelues ſhall thinke moſt meete and conuenient: neither neede to put any doubt therein, but may be aſſured that therein by vs nothing ſhal be done nor attempted. Aſſuring moreouer your Excellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. that in ſo laudable, honorable, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable, and needefull a cauſe, neither your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. nor wee, ſhall want any backing, ſupport, or ſuccour, from the neighbour Kinges, Princes, Common-weales, our neighbours and allyes. Wher<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vpon, once more moſt friendly wee require your Excellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. that you will commit to obliuion all paſſions, ſuſpitions, and former miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinges: and with this good oportunitie and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to accept and imbrace this ground, as beeing the right and onely way to bring the <hi>Netherlands</hi> into their auncient rightes, welfare, peace, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie; and to her moſt famous and flouriſhing former eſtate: without giuing any eare vnto the new pretended Forces, which are nought elſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ſuch as will cauſe a greater deſtruction &amp; miſerie. Otherwiſe, and in default hereof, wee foreſee that the damages, calamities, and miſeris, are deſtined this yeere to fall more greater, then euer hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: whereof, before all the worlde, we will be helde guiltleſſe. Heerewith, wee beſeeche th' Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD, moſt high and well Reuerent, Noble, Right Worſhipfull, Worthie, Learned,
<pb facs="tcp:26362:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->Wiſe, Prudent, and moſt diſcreete Lords, Friends, and Neighbours, to inſpire your Excellences Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Worſhips &amp;c. with that which may ſtretch to the good an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Welfare of the <hi>Netherlandes,</hi> and the good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nhabi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Geuen from <hi>S'Grauen-hage</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>7.</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e. 1602.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The Lord of <hi>Hero van Hottinga, Vt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Your Excellences, Lordſhips, Worſhips, &amp;c. good friendes and neighbours.
The generall eſtates of the vnited Prouinces: And by order of the ſame ſigned.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>C. Aerſſen.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26362:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Proclamation, or Letter of Saueguard, Which according to the former Letter of <hi>admoniſhment, is to be publiſhed to</hi> the before named Countries.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas, by meanes of the General Eſtates of th'vnited <hi>Netherlands,</hi> through the grace of GOD, the a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pote<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tates and Princes, with whom they are in league &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppe, tog<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther with their good endeuours, the welfare of the general <hi>Neth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes</hi> is intende<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: ioyntly with her deliuerance from the bondage of the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> &amp; her adherent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rame. And ſince equitie and reaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n requireth, that alſo all Prouinces, Citties, Townes, Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Inhabitantes of the <hi>Netherlandes,</hi> which are ouerburthened and ſuppreſſed by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> yoake, ſhould be aſſiſters and furtherers thereof: By theſe preſented therefore, are now for the firſt and laſt time ſummoned and admoniſhed, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Cittie of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap>  that within three dayes after the receipt hereof, they pay and deliuer into the handes of the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto our Generall Receiuer of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> being in our Campe, the ſumme of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                     </gap>  poun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, in deducting the conſented ſummes of money both heretofore borne, and hereafter to be diſburſed, for the freeing of the <hi>Netherlandes.</hi> Alſo, the ſayd Gouernours at the ſight hereof) ſhall ſende into our Campe two Pledges, for the ſayd payment: as alſo with charge, to deale further w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th our Commiſſioners, as wel vpon a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:26362:7"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->Contribution as for their defence againſt the encurſions and ſpoyles of the reſolute Souldiers of this partie: for the which, theſe preſents ſhall ſerue for a <hi>Saueguard and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſport:</hi> Or, in default of not accompliſhing theſe our Letters, we ſhall to our griefes) befores actually to proceede againſt them with the Martiall executions. Thus done, reſolued and concluded in the aſſemblie of the ſayd Lordes the generall States:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>In <hi>S'Grauen-hage</hi> 
                        <date>the. <hi>7.</hi> or June. <hi>1602.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hero van Hottinga, Vt. <hi>At the appoyntment of the aboue named Lordes the generall States.</hi> C. Aerſſen.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>BY Letters receiued from the <hi>Brill,</hi> dated the <hi>19.</hi> of June, (according vnto their Computation) is credi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly reported, that the Campe of his Excellencie <hi>Prince Maurice,</hi> was muſtered about <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tten,</hi> neare to <hi>Skencke</hi> his Scoure being in number about <hi>24000</hi> Foote men and <hi>70<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</hi> Horſe, and about <hi>2200.</hi> Wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, to each Waggon belonging three Horſe and two Men. with great quan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite of Ordenance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with drawing Horſes and their furniture therevnto belonging: Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Waggons being all laden with all neceſſarie Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntes great quantitie of Meale, Milles, Ouens to bake, S<gap reason="illegible" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>s Flayles Boates and Bridges of Leather, with other ſuch like neceſſaries: his Excellencie did begin to ſet his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l and diſcipline orders for the M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h. And was reported, that certaine Cap<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es were hanged for their falſhood and deceipt in th<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, and a Souldier, for hauing ſtollen a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the friends partie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that now each day is to be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to heare of their <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tention &amp; proceedinges; which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt dayly may and beſeech th' Almightie with his all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> giue ſuch ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſe, as ſhall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ende to the prayſe an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, the protection of his fayth, and to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
